Guide to the Mark Bowden Papers, 1972-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mark Bowden papers 1972-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bowden, Mark, 1951-
11.4 linear feet Extent: 7125 Items
Author, journalist, screenwriter, and adjunct professor at Loyola College in Maryland. Papers contain research materials for Bowden's book about the Iran hostage crisis (1979-1981), published as Guests of the Ayatollah: The First Battle in America's War with Militant Islam (NY: Atlantic Monthly Press, 2006). Materials include interview transcripts with American hostages, Iranian hostage takers, and members of the United States military who were involved in the 1980 rescue attempt. Collection also contains many research files and clippings.
RL.00131
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Electronic files are present in this collection; please consult with a reference archivist for access to these materials.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mark Bowden Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1951 Born in St. Louis, Missouri
1973 Graduated from Loyola College of Maryland with a B.A. in English Literature
1979-2003 Worked as staff writer for The Philadelphia Inquirer
1987 Published Doctor Dealer: The Rise and Fall of an All-American Boy and His Multimillion-Dollar Cocaine Empire
1994 Bringing the Heat published
1999 Publication of Black Hawk Down: A Story of Modern War
2001 Published Killing Pablo: The Hunt for the World's Greatest Outlaw
2002 Published Our Finest Day: D-Day, June 6, 1944
2002 Publication of Finders Keepers: The Story of a Man Who Found $1 Million
2006 Publication of Road Work: Among Tyrants, Heroes, Rogues, and Beasts
2006 Published Guests of the Ayatollah: The First Battle in America's War with Militant Islam
Collection Overview
The Mark Bowden Papers span the dates 1972-2004, and contain research materials for Bowden's book about the Iran hostage crisis (1979-1981), published as Guests of the Ayatollah: The First Battle in America's War with Militant Islam (NY: Atlantic Monthly Press, 2006). Materials include transcripts of Bowden's interviews with many dozens of individuals, including American hostages, Iranian hostage takers, and members of the United States military who were involved in the 1980 rescue attempt. Also present in the collection are extensive bound notebooks of press clippings, and many research files. These files contain documents related to the U.S. government's role in the hostage crisis and its relations with Iran, as well as articles by other authors on Iran and the hostage crisis. Specific materials can be found on the CIA, the Department of Defense, and President Carter's administration.
Subject Headings
Bowden, Mark, 1951-; Iran Hostage Crisis, 1979-1981 -- Chronology; Iran Hostage Crisis, 1979-1981 -- Personal narratives; Hostages -- Iran; United States -- Foreign relations -- Iran; Iran -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Armed Forces -- Search and rescue operations
Related Material
Tim Wells Papers, 1982-1986: background materials, including oral interviews, relating to Well’s book about the Iran hostage crisis (1979-1981).
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Interviews Series, 1982-2004, (9 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by last name. Consists primarily of two periods during which Bowden carried out interviews: 1982-1984 and 2002-2004. Original electronic media have been removed and files have been mounted to a library server; for access to these materials please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use the collection.
  - Ahern, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Alavitabar (Box 1)
  - Asgharzadeh (Box 1)
  - Bani-Sadr (Box 1)
  - Barnes (Box 1)
  - Belk (Box 1)
  - Brooks (Box 1)
  - Brzezinski (Box 1)
  - Cheney (Box 1)
  - Cooke (Box 1)
  - Daugherty, (Folders 1-3 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Daugherty, (Folders 1-3 of 4) (Box 2)
  - Dehnamaki (Box 2)
  - Doroski (Box 2)
  - Dwyer (Box 2)
  - Ebtekar (Box 2)
  - Engelmann (Box 2)
  - Farouz (Box 2)
  - Fitch (Box 2)
  - Gallegos (Box 2)
  - German (Box 2)
  - Golocinski, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Graves (Box 2)
  - Hall, ( 2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Hanson (Box 3)
  - Hashemi, Mohamed (Box 3)
  - Hashemi, Taha (Box 3)
  - Hermening (Box 3)
  - Holland (Box 3)
  - Hohman (Box 3)
  - Howland, John (Box 3)
  - Howland, Mike (Box 3)
  - Hughes (Box 4)
  - Jones (Box 4)
  - Kalp (Box 4)
  - Kashani (Box 4)
  - Kavakebian (Box 4)
  - Kennedy (Box 4)
  - Keough (Box 4)
  - Kirtley (Box 4)
  - Koob (Box 4)
  - Kupke (Box 4)
  - Laingen (Box 4)
  - Lee (Box 4)
  - Lenehan (Box 4)
  - Lewis (Box 4)
  - Lijek (Box 5)
  - Limbert, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Lopez (Box 5)
  - Maazroei (Box 5)
  - Metrinko (Box 5)
  - Mingo (Box 5)
  - Moadikhah (Box 5)
  - Morefield (Box 5)
  - Nabari (Box 6)
  - Naiimipoor (Box 6)
  - Needham (Box 6)
  - Nightengale (Box 6)
  - Ode, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Persinger (Box 6)
  - Pitman (Box 6)
  - Prater (Box 6)
  - Precht (Box 6)
  - Quarles (Box 6)
  - Queen (Box 7)
  - Rajaeefar (Box 7)
  - Razavi-Faqih (Box 7)
  - Roeder (Box 7)
  - Rosen (Box 7)
  - Rotundo (Box 7)
  - Royer (Box 7)
  - Savory (Box 7)
  - Schaefer, Jim (Box 7)
  - Schaefer, Thomas (Box 7)
  - Schatz (Box 7)
  - Schoomaker (Box 8)
  - Scott (Box 8)
  - Scurria (Box 8)
  - Sharer (Box 8)
  - Shariatmadari (Box 8)
  - Sharsar (Box 8)
  - Sickman (Box 8)
  - Smith (Box 8)
  - Subic (Box 8)
  - Tabatabai (Box 8)
  - Taheri (Box 8)
  - Tajzadeh (Box 8)
  - Timm (Box 8)
  - Tomseth (Box 9)
  - Turner (Box 9)
  - Uttaro, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Vaught (Box 9)
  - Walton (Box 9)
  - Yazoi (Box 9)
- Research and Writings Series, 1972-2004, (9 boxes)
  Consists primarily of research materials for the book Guests of the Ayatollah. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Abdi, Abbas (Box 9)
  - Bitaraf, Habibollah (Box 9)
  - Bound newspaper articles, 1979 Nov.-1979 Dec. (Box 9)
  - Bound newspaper articles, 1979 Dec.-1980 Apr. (Box 10)
  - Bound newspaper articles, 1980 Apr.-1980 Aug. (Box 11)
  - Bound newspaper articles, 1980 Sept.-1980 Nov. (Box 12)
  - Bound newspaper articles, 1980 Dec.-1981 Jan. (Box 13)
  - Buck, Peter, The Iranian Rescue Mission: a Case Study (Box 13)
  - Carter, Jimmy (Box 14)
    Includes correspondence, handwritten notes, speeches, and Pentagon chronology.
  - CIA documents, 1981 (Box 14)
  - Clippings, 1979-1981, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, presidential (Box 14)
    Includes Jimmy Carter, Rosalyn Carter and then-Governor Bill Clinton.
  - Current Iran, 2003, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Daugherty
    - CIA, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
    - Jimmy Carter and the decision to admit the Shah of Iran into the United States: Confustion and Questions Linger, 2003 (Box 14)
  - Desert One, (5 folders) (Box 14)
    Includes articles, Department of Defense briefing, Iranian report, House hearing testimony and other documents.
  - Diplomatic chronology, 1979-1981 (Box 15)
  - Dwyer, Cynthia (Box 15)
    Consists of correspondence, poems and a selection from memoir Women Imprisioned in the Kingdom of Mullahs.
  - Friday prayer, 2003 Sept. 28 (Box 15)
  - Guests of the Ayatollah
    - News articles and embassy files, (vols. 1 and 3) (Box 15)
    - Outline, revised (Box 15)
  - Holloway Commission Report, 1980 Aug. 23, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Hostage photos (Box 15)
  - Hostage takers (Box 16)
  - Iran book (Box 16)
  - Iranian propaganda effort after the rescue attempt (Box 16)
  - Iran, the making of U.S. Policy, 1977-1980, NS Archives, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Khomeini (Box 16)
  - Legal files, Cutler, 1980 (Box 16)
  - Memorandums, 1979-1980
    - Iran Working Group (Box 16)
    - NSC Brzezinski (Box 16)
  - Mirdamadi, Mohsen (Box 16)
  - Nightengale, Keith, Vignettes (Box 16)
  - Operation Credible Sport, 1997, 2004 (Box 17)
  - Oral Histories, (bound volume)
    - Graves, John, 1999 (Box 17)
    - Laingen, Bruce, 1993 (Box 17)
    - Morefield, Richard, 1990 (Box 17)
    - Moore, Bert, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Swift, Ann, 1992 (Box 17)
    - Precht, Henry, 2000 (Box 17)
    - Saunders, Harold, 1993 (Box 17)
  - Roeder et al. vs. Iran, transcript, 2001, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Solt, Barbara, 2002-2004 (Box 17)
    Includes articles, book reviews and thesis on former Iran hostages.
  - Spy Den, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Stock footage (Box 18)
  - Video notes (Box 18)
  - White House, 1972-1979 (Box 18)
    Includes correspondence, memorandums, intelligence assessments and presidential directives.
  - Wolf, Kendal, Iran Hostage Crisis Rescue Mission: Lessons Learned and Applied or Successes from Failure, 2004 (Box 18)
  - Moayyad, Heshmat, ed. Stories from Iran (Box 18)
  - Parsipur, Shahrmush, Women without Men (Box 18)
- Digital Material Series, (14 items)
  Contains electronic files from eight floppy disks, five cds and one mini disc of interviews.
  [Electronic files have been mounted to a library server. For access to these materials, please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use the collection.]